A Guide to the Maria von der Weppen Architectural Collection, 1978-2001
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Maria von der Weppen Architectural Collection, 1978-2001
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2001-017
9.0 cu. ft. 3 boxes, 28 tubes of drawings, 1 oversize folder
Born in 1952 in Gdynia, Poland; Maria von der Weppen studied in Poland and Norway before beginning her career in Germany. She specialized in reconstructing buildings in East Germany damaged by the war as well as new residential and office construction. Collection consist of drawings, project records, photographs, and articles relating to von der Weppen's work.
von der Weppen, Maria
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Maria von der Weppen Architectural Collection was donated to Special Collections in 2001 with the bulk of the collection arriving in 2007.
Biographical Note
Maria von der Weppen was born on July 18, 1952 in Gdynia, Poland. von der Weppen studied architecture at Technical University of Gdansk in Poland (1971-1975). From 1976 to 1978 she continued her studies at the Oslo School of Architecture and Design while working at the architectural office of Trygve Kleiven.
In the summer of 1979 Maria moved to Berlin, Germany and worked for several firms, including BSM Berlin a consulting company for urban planning and modernism. In 1984 she opened her own architectural office and spent her private practice focusing on the reconstruction of structures damaged by World War II. Her works ranged from historic buildings and neighborhoods to new housing and office complexes. In 1995 after political changes, von der Weppen applied her experience in Poland beginning with the rehabilitation and restoration of a church in Slonsk/Sonnenburg. Thereafter she divided her time between Germany and Poland.
Scope and Content
von der Weppen's collection encompasses work from her private practice (1985 to 2001) as well as some examples from her academic career. In the collection you will find school work, drawings, photographs, and manuscript material relating to her projects. Materials range in date from 1978-2001 and contain professional papers and project records. Review the contents list below for details on individual categories.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Architectural drawing--20th century.; International Archive of Women in Architecture (IAWA); Women-owned architectural firms.
Genre and Form Terms:
Architectural drawings.
Occupations:
Architects.
Contents List
- SERIES I: Personal Papers, 1978 and undated
  - Student Work in Norway
    - Musicshop (Box 1:1, Box 30)
    - Ferrbyboot Terminal (Box 19)
    - Kulturhus (Box 20)
    - Ungdomsskole på Høybråten, Spring 1978 (Oversize Folder 1)
  - Student Work in Poland (Box 8, Box 10, Box 12, Box 27, Box 23, Box 14)
- SERIES II:Professional Papers, 1995, 1998
  - Photographs of Exhibit Panels for UIFA Tokyo (1998) (Box 19)
  - Resume (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Publication: (1995) Villa vom Keller bis zum Dach auf Fußboden-heizung eingestalt. Bauen Wohnen Freizeit, 38-41 (Box-folder 1:3)
- SERIES III: Projects, 1987-2001
  - Sanierung Danckelmannstr. 1 Berlin-Charlottenburg (1987) (Box-folder 1:5, Box 28)
  - Medusentor (Text u. Photos) 1989 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Neubau Wohn-und Praxisanlage Wöbelin (1990) (Box 7)
  - Wettbewerb Bebauung August-Bebel-Siedlung Kleinmachnow (1990-1991) (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Sanierung und Dachausbau August-Bebel-Siedlung Kleinmachnow (1990-1992) (Box 26)
  - Neubau Virchowstr. 11 Potsdam (1991-1993) (Box-folder 1:8, Box 21, Box 31)
  - Neubau und Bebauungsplan KLM-BP-008 Kleinmachnow (1991-1992) (Box-folder 1:9, Box 19)
  - Neubau planung einer Wohn-Gewerbe-und Industrieanlage Potsdamer Allee 109/111 Stahnsdorf (1994) (Box 25, Box-folder 1:10-11)
  - Rekonstruktion eines Wohn-bäudes Virchow Str. 49, Potsdam (1994) (Box 3, Box 13)
  - Neubau Gardes-du-Corps Str. 18, Berlin-Charlottenburg (1985) [Ms, Dr, Ph] (Box-folder 1:4, Box 22)
  - Modernisierung und Instand-setzung eines Wohngebäudes Virchowstr. 13, Potsdam (1995) (Box 3, Box 6)
  - Umbau/Erweiterung Barnewitz (1995) (Box 4)
  - Sanierung und Ausbau Dieselstr. 52/ Heinrich-von Kleist-Str. 18, Potsdam (1996-1997) (Box 3, Box-folder 2:1-2, Box 29)
  - DG-Ausbau Dankelmannstr. 1/Gardes-du-Corps-Str. 18 Berlin-Charlottenburg (1996-1997) (Box 9)
  - 4 Alternativplanungen einer moglichen Bebauung Virchowser. 42/Karl-Marx-Str. 16 Postdam (1997) (Box 18)
  - Neubau Wohnanlage Dallgow (1997) (Box 11, Box-folder 2:3)
  - Instandsetzung und Modernisierung Krossenerstr. 19/Gabriel-Max-Str. 5, Berlin-Friedrichshain (1999-2001) (Box 5, Box 3)
  - Vobereitende Untersuchung Zum Sanierungsbebiet "Bosch-Siedlung" (undated) (Box-folder 2:4, Box 16, Box 17, Box 24)
  - BV Klingsortiaße 13 berlin-Steglitz Erweiterung eines Konditorei Betriebs (undated) (Box 15)